so I had this this incident yesterday
that I would say unfortunately is not a
rare incident where I am couldn't find
one of my socks so of course I start
doing this very familiar dance called
looking for my sock at some point I'm
kind of alerted by my wife Brianne
asking me what are you looking for and
all of a sudden I realize and I had this
kind of blank look on my face and
Brianne smiles and she's like you forgot
what you're looking for didn't you this
moment of and we both laugh and and I
remembered oh I was looking for my sock
he's funny because that strangely that
I've been thinking about that at the
edge of my awareness you know since
since that happened yesterday and I
somehow it's if there's something
there's something about that right that
I think is speaks to something that I I
want to see if I can kind of tease out
what it would it what's kind of
disclosed in that right so it's like
it's funny right it's it's a funny thing
because you know we you could say we
have this ability right to to look for
something and start looking for it
and in the process of looking for it not
notice that we've forgotten what we're
looking for yet still be looking and
it's it's not that I you know in that
moment when I'm looking for my sock it's
not like I'm present to not knowing what
I was looking for cuz if I were I
wouldn't be looking I'd be thinking
about what the hell I was looking for no
there's this little period of time right
where I'm looking and it's it's lost to
me that I've lost what I'm looking for
it's concealed
and I've been thinking about like you
know it's funny it's it's what else is
that like you know this ability to on
some level to be on our way towards
something which is you know on some
level that's what it is to be a person
we're always on our way somewhere always
on our way somewhere we're always coming
from somewhere and it seems that there's
a way in which what has us what calls us
into being on our way in a very deep
level can be concealed to us and it can
be concealed that is concealed and I
imagine this is what in us in a in a in
a way is what you know the Greeks really
meant by the term Alafaya or ilithyia
which is the okay you could say the
primordial notion of truth and it's
really interesting because it's not
truth as we usually think of it now
which is correctness right where when
the something like the word and the
object align up the idea of the mind and
the object of the world light not they
correlate and we call that true that's
true
correct yet you know that as the Greeks
do have a much more primordial notion of
truth which is the you could say the
happening the event the the moment where
that which is veiled hidden
becomes revealed right in this
interesting because for the longest time
you know I've been thinking about
ilithyia for a long time because it
seems to me that right that the that
when we have it's always struck me that
that this kind of double this double
experience of personal insights that I
would have and then I'd be in the
presence of people having you know and
and my work and stuff it's always struck
by this kind of double sense where
there's like an insight means like you
see something new but you also reveal if
it's an insight that which was already
the case but concealed from you and so
when I started understanding this term
Alafaya as truth I think there's that
that's you know that really spoke to me
but the thing about that is like for the
at first I thought well you know it's
about what's revealed right so there was
something hidden and it's revealed and
like the truth is what is revealed but I
don't think that's the case and I think
I think this sense of looking for the
sock that was concealed that I had
totally forgotten it but yet was still
given by then the the the forgotten
looking for sickness I was still looking
for it right this ability to to be
constituted great to be characterized by
such a activity and be completely
consistent have it be completely
concealed right speaks to this in this
funny way right
where you know it's I think that the
word comes from lazy it comes from the B
the Greek myth I think it's a river or a
lake and it's considered lay Thea I
consider the river or the lake of
forgetfulness so to get a sense of this
it's like it's forgetfulness so you know
if I'm guys walking along and he trips
and falls into lake lake here it's not
like people are like whoa
where's guy no it's guy becomes
forgotten right and so it's missing that
guy's missing it's forgotten
that guy is forgotten total concealment
so Alethea is not the realization of guy
that that is the case but the thing that
the thing that's really disclosed right
is the recognition that it was
completely concealed to you
it's that that's the thing that evokes
it's the uncanny 'no so that of how
deeply that can feel this is it's a
strange thing to try to put words to
however I think it's worth it because
and some level it just seems like it
seems like that's kind of where being is
and this also strikes me the more modern
we are the less and less that sense this
sensitivity to the nothing to the edge
of our intelligibility let we have less
and less of a sense for this nothing for
this not yet on some level it's like the
anonymous one that sits before under
within everything else and little
moments like that right little
little moments like that reveals this
kind of uncanny this of that which is
deeply silent
so having ears having eyes having you
know what is it to be become sensitive
to be struck by those little moments of
wear concealment reveals itself and I
think the key is right the key is and
poetry this is one of things I love
about poetry because it has this sense
where it can it can reveal the concealed
right without making it unconcealed no
another way of saying that is it's a way
in which it can presents the unknown
without making it known because the
being